[Music]
all right
hello and welcome everyone it's
actimflab livestream number 41.0
on april 2nd 2022 foursquare two comma
two zero two two
we're discussing the paper extended
active inference constructing predictive
cognition beyond skulls
so welcome to the actin flab everyone
we're a participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at some of the links here
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following good
video etiquette for live streams
head over to
activeinference.org to learn more about
what is happening in act lab
we're here today in active stream number
41.0 where we are learning and
discussing the paper extended active
inference constructing predictive
cognition beyond skulls by axel constant
andy clark
michael kirchoff and carl firsten
from december 2020
so long ago
and this video is an introduction for
some of the ideas and some of the pieces
of the paper it's not a review or a
final word and the dot one is just
us getting excited and
doing our preparation so that the dot
one and the dot two the participatory
group discussions we can start to unpack
them
more
we're going to go over some aims and
claims keywords the abstract and the
roadmap of the paper
address the big question and then walk
through some of the figures and
formalisms and
the coming weeks we'll have
a.1.2
which of course are open to anyone who
wants to join
so we'll just begin by saying hello and
any thoughts we have
i'm
daniel i'm a researcher in california
and on the topic of distributed or
extended cognitive processes dean really
appreciated
co
stigmatically
extended in space and time collaborating
with you on the slides
um i loved your first pass on the slides
and it just
made me remark on how different it is um
to be involved in a distributed
cognitive process versus the kind that
can just play out in the quiet room
within the skull and that's like just
one example of what this whole paper and
extended mind extended cognitive area is
about is actually
among other things respecting those
kinds of processes and thinking about
how to frame them so that is obviously
something we'll be talking
about a lot more
over to you
hi uh my name is dean i'm up here in
calgary and i think what i really liked
about this paper
is
their ability to sort of say
um
there's some ways that we've been
looking at this question of how far does
the process
go and then there's
this paper
which introduces a new way of maybe
having a conversation around that they
talk about things like
uploading
uh entailing some of the more nascent
features of offloading and so
that to me
has the potential of morphing because
we've done a lot of morphology lately
from subject matter expertise to
prediction matter expertise if
somebody
can also hold up an egg and a chicken
for example so i'm kind of excited about
that
okay
excellent into the paper we go
so the paper link is provided here and
as stated it's from 2020.
um i'll just
uh
well why don't you summarize what you
felt some of the
key aims and claims were
uh
well i'll summarize aims you you can
summarize the claims for me the aim was
to be able to optimize organize
organisms generative models which
a cognitive niche construction
implies but these authors essentially
sort of
put that out there in a
they articulate that
it reviews generic predictive approaches
to niche construction
it takes
and looks at both the functional and the
psychological components of what
that active
generation of a cognitive niche might be
and then they argue for and i think this
is the critical bullet an extended
active inference henceforth e a i based
on our model of cognitive niche
construction so there's a model within
the modeling universe
this is theirs
excellent yes as we'll explore
they aim towards reconciling some of the
functional and grounded and embodied
aspects of what is known as the
cognitive niche with some of the
essentially metaphysical in the sense
that they're not as embodied they're
like purely cognitive features of or
psychological features of the cognitive
niche so that's kind of where they aim
and yes they aim for a synthesis
reflected in the eai idea
so some of the
claims in
the paper so these are things where it's
like you could ask whether these are
valid assertions or assumptions
cognitive niche construction which again
they're thinking of in a functional and
psychological sense
is the process whereby organisms create
and maintain cause effect models of
their niche as guides for fitness
influencing behavior so it's kind of
like extended autopoesis
self-maintenance but not just at the
level of the epithelia like a cognitive
boundary
extended mind theory claims that
cognitive processes extend beyond the
brain to include predictable states the
world
statistical
regularities in the generative process
and how to leverage those processes
active inference and predictive
processing in cognitive science assume
that organisms embody predictive
which is generative models of the world
optimized by standard cognitive
functions
like perception action learning and so
putting
different cognitive features on common
grounding
those are some of the
aims and claims of the paper
let's see how they get there
here's a few of the keywords that were
in the paper active inference
affordances
capacities for action availabilities for
action
cognitive niche construction which we'll
go into a lot more
ecological psychology
which is
something that's been around for decades
it's about breaking the psyche out of
the skull
and that's very related to extended mind
and then predictive processing and this
sort of anticipatory perspective
and the real time signal processing
action loop all these things that are
like
active by another word or kind of like
the latent
proto-active threads that um are brought
together here
anything to add on keywords
no
okay i'll read the abstract and then you
can feel free to give a thumb
cognitive niche construction is the
process whereby organisms create and
maintain cause effect models of their
niche as guides for fitness influencing
behavior
extended mind theory claims that
cognitive processes extend beyond the
brain to include predictable states of
the world
active inference and predictive
processing and cognitive science assume
that organisms embody predictive ie
generative models of the world optimized
by standard cognitive functions eg
perception action learning
this paper presents an active inference
formulation that views cognitive niche
construction as a cognitive function
aimed at optimizing organisms generative
models
we call that process of optimization
extended active inference
what do i think what do i think about
that i i think of it from the from the
view of
a professional setting as an example of
an environment
and how that professional setting
traditionally is
not necessarily seeing
the agents within it like
we sometimes consider the internalities
within the epithelial
limits
but
we very much depend on those things
functioning correctly so
this kind of opens up a little
tiny portal into how our imaginations
might
be able to sort of um
access them
it makes me think about like the
professional setting
the professional niche
is that something that's just reflected
in the skull of the expert or the
professional as a person
or is the setting something that's
distributed where
it wouldn't be possible to locate or
focalize it within the skull of any
individual
while also recognizing for example that
um a lesion inside of the skull of a
person in a professional setting would
change it so we don't need to like deny
brain functionalism
to have an extended yes and approach to
cognitive systems so what are we going
to find to have when we go down that way
um well here's some of the signposts
along that way
this is their roadmap how they get from
discussing previous work in the extended
mind and cognitive niche area towards
their concept of extended extended
active inference
the introduction covers some of the core
background concepts like cognitive niche
active inference and the extended mind
they then kind of lay out where they're
going to go in section two the
functional and psychological niches
under active inference
they partition or delineate different
ways of thinking about the cognitive
niche into a psychological and a
functional component and then present a
case study
um there's also figures that we'll walk
through and
through the presentation of this
disambiguation of cognitive niche and
case study in connection to the active
inference models they present
extended active inference eai
and then discuss several features or
aspects of eai like the parity principle
which we'll come back to of course
functional isomorphisms epistemic
actions and diachronic cognition under
eai
anything to add on the roadmap
no i'll let's get the big question here
go for the big question
okay i'll just read it off the slide
here the set of questions that fall
within our scope relates to the
computational function of cognitive
extensions and the developmental and
intergenerational so we're going to talk
about a little bit of a temporal thing
here process whereby this computational
function emerges given
the on the cognitive niche is sometimes
studied as a psychological habitat
refers to the set of organisms niche
relations
that offer organisms relevant
affordances
and two the cognitive niche is sometimes
studied as a functional habitat refers
to the set of resources that support
species specific tasks
that's the behavior angle then this
means that one must define the
functional habitat on the background of
the organism's phenotypic dispositions
this is where daniel's expertise can
step in for example books are part of
the functional habitats of humans
because of humans ability to read
but they're not part of the beaver's
functional habitat unless of course the
beaver wants to include it as part of
their
environmental structure which
if they're an imaginal beaver maybe they
do
the psychological and functional
habitats can be part of the same overall
physical habitat
my question then was how then do
cognitive extensions exist we're not
answering that today
but we're parking that for future
conversation
there's a famous quote in biology
nothing makes sense except in the light
of evolution and a million other
mutations on that and we've talked about
eco evo devo in biology like the
importance of thinking holistically
about ecology and evolution and
development processes that entail
different mechanisms and play out over
different scales to influence phenotype
as studied
and
what i see
here is
ecology
which has been dancing with cognition
that's the ecological cognitive area
ecological psychology
then there's developmental
psychology
of course how does learning happen and
then there's evolutionary psychology and
any of those fields people can take or
leave but it's almost like we're going
to
um
dissolve those
couplets
into just eco evo and devo pull them
away from the cognition from
developmental ecological and
evolutionary cognition
and then like
bring it all back together so no one's
denying that humans don't read books or
that beavers don't make a damn or
anything like that so what are we really
getting at here it's a different way to
recombine and
reframe
how we think about
cognition and ecology
can i just add one thing to that because
that's that's
thank you
a decade and even two two decades ago
there's a real push of real
philosophical um
density forming around the idea of
hands-on science
but this questions what can we get our
hands on
because if again if you want to simplify
it let's just say oh if we give
everybody a chance to
touch the beaver kit that will somehow
change their understanding of beaver
behavior
um what you just described says know
what that will give us is an
understanding of
the the direction that their fur
um all seems to set up as right so
again we have to be careful that we
don't come up with these oh
here's here's the way to solve all of
these really complex issues
the hands-on example also um
it made me think about how you could
still have a very brain-based approach
to thinking about hands-on cognition
some could say it's been shown that when
there's multi-sensory engagement that
the learner updates their cognitive
model more rapidly so multi-sensory
learning or experience driven learning
is more engaging for science it keeps
people in the game longer they learn the
concepts better
absolutely that is still within the
individual
intra skull paradigm
but it starts moving into the periphery
and the parry personal space
and it's like
is this extended cognitive process
aren't the hands always on something or
i'm sure there's right now are they
literally
are they on are they on an abstraction
that's the big question right so yeah it
gets really interesting in a hurry it's
if you want to take a a quantum bike
ride with chris fields
you got to be able to explain how that
how that works so
another piece i just can't help but it's
from the academic textbook
i can't help myself
i have a new car i have to drive it
um
this is on the first page of the preface
to illustrate the simplicity of active
inference and what we are trying to
explain place your fingertips gently on
your leg keep them there motionless for
a second or two now does your leg feel
rough or smooth
if you had to move your fingers to
events a feeling of roughness or
smoothness you have discovered a
fundament of active inference to feel is
to palpate to see is to look to hear is
to listen
so if you can't with your hands on with
a finger on
if the pants don't have a feeling of
smoothness or roughness
except for as a function
of action
what are we handling grasping
comprehending
right with cognitive
things
right
that that whole niche development thing
which we're going to get into today
all right awesome so cognitive niche
section 111.
do you want to give a first summary on
any parts you think are important well i
i'm going to just read some of the stuff
from the paper itself i i threw a few
references in here as well but
i mean cognitive science a form of
instrumental intelligence
uh to be into devore if i hope i'm
pronouncing that correctly create and
maintain cost effect models of the world
as guides
for prejudging which courses of action
will lead to which results
we've had a few conversations about
guides in the in the new year 2022 so
that was i thought that was interesting
residues in the environment act as cues
and prompts
concept development niche
as where and when your genes are act
given the epigenetic epigenetic envelope
over
niche as genetic information inherited
i thought that that that made a clear
differentiation
uh the concept of cognitive
cognitive niche that we're referring to
here is a sort of hybrid again i love
this
between the concepts of the selected
developmental and cognitive niches
this paper questions
this paper's questions fall under
that which conceptual function emerges
comp sorry computational function
emerges
um
so the so bottom line is they say that
there are there are
things in the
in the timeline of the environment
which
are passed along
so how do we explain that
through
a lot of different ways but active
inference in particular and so that's
what this is about and so again i threw
a a couple of different ways in terms of
explaining the cognitive load aspect of
that like why would we
download or offload or upload into the
environment and why would the next
generation necessarily be able to pick
up on that
through some sort of pointing or signal
signaling effort
what were you getting at with
the cognitive niche for enabling
somebody to learn and apply active
inference and about how that relates to
professional or other settings inside
and outside of academia
well the enabling part is what i was
really wondering about so how is is that
set up
is there a set the condition for that or
are what they describing here as is
something
variant
retained
meaning condition set
right because there's always a tendency
to want to say okay well things are too
complicated so let's focus on
x
right
and that was my essentially what my
question was here is is the
interdisciplinary question satisfied
by organizing along chapters and subject
areas because we just don't want to
overload people right i mean we get why
we do it there's a reason for it and
that's what they're talking about here
there's a reason why
there are tracks laid down in the
environment that can help guide the next
passing passer through right but the
bottom line is
um
is the constructionism aspect of this
mechanics part of it
the default or functional enhancement
outside of the academic niche like when
you get out of school
what do you do
do you necessarily follow the same
patterns that you do in school
how does a bridge to uncertainty as a
metaphor change the nature from
explanatory to exploration and back
so when we go out into the world and
then come back into academia how does
that change our perception of the
structures that academia places down to
make sure that we get to certain
outcomes relative to the variance that
still exists out there in the greater
space
makes me think of uh paths in a forest
and it's like
is
within a generation
or between generations
are we trying to pass down the path
or are we passing down a healthy forest
where wayfinding can happen
and it's like well i paved the path and
i removed all the brambles from it
where's the forest now because in order
to make that path stabilized
the functional niche had to actually
change and so that
um shows how like the cognitive and the
functional niche start to have interplay
over these multiple
time scales
yep
all right great
1.1.2 here's where they uh
introduce the concept of active
inference
what parts did you pull out on the left
side like what text pieces did you find
important
well before we get about before we talk
about starting and pronging yeah no i
just highlight where i thought it was
kind of interesting is if you just read
the stuff that's um fonted in red
you have to entertain there's a
probabilistic relationship we have to
think of this not just over a single
time frame but
over as you said over pulse possible
inference probability and modeling
time frames um what's entailing what
when we're talking through the active
inference lens
transitions amongst causes
interesting so processes of processes
um
the updating piece
right and so
again
the the starting the procking thing all
i did wanted to do is in that section of
the paper say here's an example in in
the in the wild
where we could identify each one of the
aspects that they were talking about in
this section of the paper
and you had listed a few
um functions or a few
as here and then i added a few more
and i think it just reflected how
there's
always a plurality of answers to the y
question
in biology
we have tim bergen's for whys and we
have
different time scales and whether the
proximate or the ultimate cost all this
stuff that we've talked about other
times and then just even within the
active perspective
why
do these animals do this jumping
behavior
and
how does active inference help us think
about that kind of behavior like it's a
signal to itself about its bodily
integrity and its coherence in its
capacity
it's a signal to other entities like
itself like other con specifics for
example an early warning system for a
predator
it also
has been brought up
in the literature that this is actually
uh honest and costly signal to the
predator
like
look at me jump and play you think
you're going to get me that's absurd go
after somebody who's not jumping and
playing
um
and then there's so many other ways like
to think about it and those are
things that you could disambiguate you
might be able to design and experiment
or a professional setting to reduce your
uncertainty or to
engineer and scaffold
something
but once you get
this deer in the lab
on the trampoline in the vr headset with
the predators approaching from both
sides when that doesn't happen in the
wild
what are you actually studying
right
i like the last bullet too because it
could be
pronounced as way updating or way up
dating
so i mean anytime we and i i i i hope
people appreciate that it could
literally
be interpreted both ways and that's what
i think is kind of fascinating about
this paper
is that inversion
in our minds of what so what is that
just put placing the emphasis
reinforces two very different concepts
yes
and to close this set of introductory
concepts the cognitive niche active
inference and we get to the extended
mind concept so
what pieces did you find relevant here
and what did you pull out of the text
itself and associated citations
well just for me it was an affirmation
of what i've been thinking about for a
long time that the idea of
saying
something is something is contained in
your skull and and shall no further pass
doesn't get answered just because we can
communicate back and forth to one
another there's probably a lot more
evidence in the larger environment if
you
take the time to look for it and it
doesn't always necessarily cause issues
in terms of what you
can or or can't
imagine
so those images out there
are
are collective and so do we always come
at it from the perspective of
we're making connections because there
are associations and we get that but is
there an uploading aspect of this that
quite literally in in the in the
community can look like a museum
right so
these these ways of being able to
understand what's happening
have other ways than what has
traditionally been thought of as here's
where something ends
and something else
begins
one piece i thought was interesting
this is kind of a classic modern example
of extended minds
so they discuss
reliable access to external states the
niche eg the cell phone that functions
as an extended memory
for recalling phone numbers
okay how about when those are your cloud
contacts and now that phone is pinging a
global communications network
so again no one is denying that an
entity can take an action that triggers
computational events and
cognitive events to occur around the
world and beyond sending those signals
off into wherever so
what are we actually
discussing what is extended relative to
what again reifying the epithelial
boundary and saying well it's extended
relative to the epithelial boundary but
isn't this about updating our priors to
think about cognition in a more extended
way
so then
why do the sort of straw person version
of epithelial individualist
brain-centered cognition
and then posit extended cognition as a
contrast from that like what is the real
positivist
um or positive
claim
in extended
cognition and there's a lot of
interesting citations here back through
the decades and
people have been talking about the stuff
for a very
long time so that'll be a cool like
thread to draw on yeah
yeah what's interesting is i've had
conversations with sweller and gins
back you know like 15 years ago
about this whole question of what is
cognitive overload and one of my one of
my favorite references is lucy sukeman's
the human machine interface where her
her book is essentially set up as a case
study around
people encountering
the
photocopy machine
and
what exactly transpires there as as an
extended mind because there's people
that have sort of built the photocopy
machine in the hopes that it becomes
intuitive
but as she points out in a reference
well that's
that's in the eye of the beholder that's
in the person who has to key in their
passcode and then
try to try to determine of course the
person who's actually built a photocopy
machine try to determine how each one of
those individuals with each separate
passcode necessarily
believes that their mind is being
extended so that they don't have to
you know as stephen used to do make
another copy and make another copy and
make another copy right so there's a
there's a lot in this
and
it's it can't always be
reduced down to
an assumption around
a particular order of steps that will
just naturally seem
present to the person who now has their
hand available
and and a screen from which they can
select a number of options but still
can't get what inside of their head they
want
in terms of that version or that format
so anyway it's
i love the extended mind concept but now
how how do we employ it in such a way
that it be actually is something
available as opposed to just theoretical
it makes me think of playing pool or
billiards so in the extended desire to
move the ball from one area to another
like you use a q and it's like
transducing mechanical force and then
that force is transmitted to the um ball
that you strike and that has all these
outcomes in the board
what is the pool cue
but these increasingly abstract
processes we talk about the grip and the
embodied performance the skilled
performance of playing pool and all of
those aspects and again how do we talk
about epistemic grip and we're extending
not just into the functional niche so
like the real phenotypic substrates but
when we start thinking about as the
authors reminded us
of selective developmental and cognitive
niches this is like
apples and oranges and kale chips over
different time scales it's not just
counting how many pieces of fruit are on
the table these are different nested
interacting and even types
of things so how do we keep all of that
on the menu
and still
do
yeah and you introduced with the pool
cue a field thing
which is in zukman's
reference she talks about feel thing
it's not just the touching of a screen
there's a huge feel component to this
that's often left out but can't be if
we're talking about extending our minds
it makes me think about putting the
chalk on the tip of the queue and that
helps the pool tip
um make grip with the ball better
but you wouldn't put the the blue chalk
on
you know
your feet on the ground like the way
that they grip the ground is different
than how the extended
cognitive apparatus gets a grip and
that's like where we see a lot of
challenges in programming somebody with
skill and programming goes well of
course that's not going to work because
like to get a grip on this process this
program needs the api call to look like
this and then it can get a handle it can
get a web hook it can make this call so
that on the other side of the phone the
right other program calls back but
here's the other person still you know
shining their shoe with the blue chalk
and wondering why the billiards not
going the right direction
okay
perfect here we get to their outline and
argument so
what would you say is important about
what they wrote here with all of these
different cues that we have annotated
and added into the text
well what i appreciate is that there
in order to be able to introduce the
concept of uploading which we'll get to
here they're basically saying so
and i don't want to put words in the
author's mouths but in
my interpretation of what i read was
this is why it's taking so long
because they're going to cut into a a
time a temporal piece to this eventually
anyway and and
rather than read all of the of the uh
highlighted parts that i i dragged out
i'll let you
maybe you want to talk about the things
that you think
for the point one and point two
we might wanna spend a little bit more
time on i'd like when you're done i'd
like to talk about stuff in the on the
right-hand side of the page
excellent just a few pieces that would
be cool to unpack would be salience and
attention
and ascent of cues in communication
and how sometimes cues can be transient
like what i'm about to say next is
really important but then other times
cues can be
acting through time like stigmergy so
epistemic cues as ecological legacies is
really powerful
guiding epistemic foraging
um
the notion of a shared
cognitive model
but once it becomes one shared cognitive
model is it extended anymore
or by drawing the boundaries around that
shared model is it saying well it's not
extended within
so um
i think
optimization leveraging of shared
generative models through action and
perception
excellence place to pick up as we think
about
our intra actin flab and other contexts
share generative models um cognitive
uploading
one place to
start there would be like what is being
appealed to or invoked with this upload
download metaphor how many
kb per second are we talking about what
are we getting at or potentially seeing
only one facet of when we use this
computationalist notion of up and down
load
which they do unpack
and
also the idea of cognitive extensions
that gain independence from the specific
individuals having produced them
so it's kind of like if the ex the cool
queue
doesn't
do a different type of thing
but then as people might be interested
in
more and more autonomous pool cues
allowing them to be further and further
from more and more complex pool tables
until they're not even looking at the
pool table
they're just sending a sequence of
messages to something that is
outside of the person who designed it it
wouldn't even be called a pool cue but
all of a sudden it's so extended
it's involving all this cyber physical
apparatus that it does have this degree
of
autonomy or independence from the
individuals who created them so then
where do we put these complex cyber
physical systems where it's like it's
not dr frankenstein nor is it dr
frankenstein's monster
what is really
the cognitive apparatus in those
situations what about what you see on
the right side
well i want to just before i go to that
i want to just say because i i put on
that thing there professional niches
programming and i'm not
not horn tuning here but basically that
was the name of the
that was the name of the company that i
started up and ran for a decade and
essentially the reason why i put it in
there is because to the point uh the
optimization and leveraging of the
shared generative model sharing through
action and perception or what we
call extended active inference
when that's actually applied and you
actually see
people doing something with that
uh
it it's actually quite fascinating
because it's actually very distributed
you don't have a job wall and then
people decide whether or not the things
that are on offer are things that they
want to partake in what it does is it's
an inversion of that it's essentially
saying
um
are you an explorer by nature
and if you are are there other explorers
out there in the larger community who
that relational
frame is something that you could share
so again this these are interesting
things that this paper now
surfaces so
i just want to talk about that for a
second so my my questions were should we
assume that the exploration done in
literature is a proxy for functioning in
the wild we take maps with us
but do we continue to stare at the maps
while we're in the wild
how much focus on the epistemic resolves
what when which questions to predict
when the bird strike happens
right these random things
are are how do we respond to randomness
and then how does the hudson river take
care of cognitive extension gain because
that seems like a weird question to ask
but in the context of this paper
that's the question that's being asked
so
don't be afraid
ask it
don't be scared
because the alternative is a lot worse
right
that's what's fascinating about the
sort of creative part of this that
active inference i think enables
but it's it's not
it's not constructivist it's
creativist and i'm not saying that there
isn't a huge constructivist piece here
but you're leaving off another
magnificent part of it if you only focus
on the computational and the
constructivist
excellent a lot more to say on that but
let's move forward to section two
we're gonna now talk about active
inference entailing functional and
psychological niches okay so here's
where we get to equation one
and they write a generative model which
is this left term here with a purple
line
is a probabilistic statement about a set
of unobserved hidden variables i.e
hypothesized causes
like you didn't actually see the
lightning strike but there's going to be
some unobserved cause which is like the
actual event of the lightning initiation
and observed sensations i.e consequences
so that could be like the volume and the
visual input of thunder and lightning
which represents an organism's
predictive or causal model of the world
that's that joint generative model
a generative model is usually expressed
in terms of a likelihood and a prior
term and this is sort of like um a
fundamental statistical
tool slash trick slash tip
that you can take a joint distribution
and then kind of pull out and condition
upon
one of the variables in that joint
distribution so it's like probability of
flipping a coin rolling a die
it's like flipping a coin condition on
rolling a die multiplied by rolling the
die but not exactly in this likelihood
prior case but it's very much too
similar so quick question for you can
you can you tell me when you say trick
is it is as simple as a flip
like
effect cause
cause effect is it is that what you mean
by trick
like a hot trick
well like a a pattern of performance
that enables you
to win statistical games
okay okay
but of course anyone can describe it
however else they want so
here they're saying the likelihood
corresponds to the probability of
sensations
given the priors
and then the prior corresponds to the
probability of the conditions or causes
that generate the sensations
so this is like beliefs about how the
world is
in the prior
and then this is the likelihood of
sensations which is here s
conditioned upon those beliefs of the
world
and uh two other places to
learn a little bit more would be um
active stream number 34 where we were
discussing
axel's paper
free energy principle it's not about
what it takes it's about what took you
there we talked a lot about bays exact
bays variational bays and about free
energy minimization and when do priors
go right when do they go wrong
and then here is an example from
the active textbook from 2022
and on page 18
they show an example with frog and apple
that's the hidden state of the world
what is actually in your hand is it a
frog or an apple
and so initially there's a prior belief
like 90 percent that it's an apple and
10 that it's a frog
and then there's this observation of
jumping which could be like vis visual
it could be
tactile proprioceptive etc and then that
has an associated likelihood model of
apples jump one percent of the time
frogs are jumping 81 of the time
and then it's like much more likely that
jumping is a frog than an apple
people can see that and then that
updates the prior belief into a
posterior belief but it never eradicates
the alternative it's still 10 percent
likely that it's an apple that jumped
because initially we thought it was like
very likely so that's just one example
from the book
let's see how we actually use that
generative model decomposition into
likelihood and prior to talk about
functional and psychological niche
they're going to use variational
inference to invert this likelihood
which is the statistical distribution of
sensations given causes of the world
so how you should interpret a given
sensation
conditioned upon your beliefs about how
things actually are out there
to
um
approximate the posterior probability of
causes
once a sensation has been sampled so
here it's p
s conditioned upon
eta
oh that's the right um pronunciation of
fancy n
um but here we're looking for actually
the probability distribution on
unobserved causes of the world
conditioned upon observed sensations so
these are like two of the directions of
cognition given
the prior on what's out there in the
world
what is being sensed
and then this is
given the sensations
what is out there in the world
so the big picture level this is like
how we're both doing inference on
perceiving the lightning and thunder and
the actual likelihood of what's
happening in that cloud out there
despite not being able to directly
observe it
so that's the inversion that they're
talking about here and that could be
done through
different methods but the variational
approach
allows this inversion to be done in like
a tractable and computable way
and so here they're gonna use the same
notation
and they're just gonna unpack it into
equation two and they write the
variational density becomes a posterior
belief
so that's a prior that's been updated by
input about the causes of sensations
given
um the sensations that were experienced
this inverse mapping from causes to
effect corresponds to inferring the
causes of sensations so
in a way we repeat ourselves many times
with this inversion in both directions
at once
and
i hope it's just not redundant for those
who are familiar nor
ambiguous overly for those who are
unfamiliar but this is sort of at the
core of it is that there's modeling of
both the sensations and the underlying
causes
and sometimes it goes from one to the
other
and backwards
and variational inference is like a
toolbox or a toolkit that helps deal
with both of those directions and
compute them in a tractable way
and here's the thing it's if if
if you
if you think you can analogize this too
i've always walked around on my feet and
now i'm going to walk around on my hands
that's not what's actually happening
here that's not the type of inversion
that's actually going on here there's
there's something to do with effect and
cause
that doesn't just necessarily translate
to what's up and what's down you have to
take more a little bit more
dimensionality into that
and so that's
that's why it remains at sort of this
mathematical statistical level
as opposed to oh if it was just as
simple as oh you're telling me now to
walk around in my hands and that's going
to change my perspective no that's not
what we're saying here
just to give kind of one reading of
equation two so this f it's very much
spaced out but you can think of it as
being like f of x like a function f of
the variable x like with x as an
argument but you could think about that
f being like right here it's a
functional it's a function of
states that are sensations s and mu the
internal states and like it's kind of
like here the eta is the external it's
like an upside down view so mu is
internal and then it says external
and so that free energy value for a
given combination of sensation and
internal which are to say cognitive
states is the divergence between
the truth the true posterior which is
the actual distribution of causes given
sensations
and this q distribution q sub mu so it's
a q distribution that we control as a
cognitive state that takes only a single
argument which is just eta
and then that kl divergence which is
trying to minimize the difference
between like the q distribution that we
control and the true posterior
and subtracting out just how surprising
given stage should be
we talk about it also other times but
many touches many coats of paint so
we'll continue on
what is this variational inference
approach allow
that takes us to equation three formally
variational inference
converts an inference problem
into an optimization problem
as articulated by equation three and
figure one so here's our figure two
which was stated as like an inference
problem
and then this is going to move to
um an optimization problem
using this arg min which just means like
choose the minimum choose the minimum of
that argument
um over q
and then that is going to be applied to
this inverse mapping
they also connected here to
some discussion of bayes optimal
updating
when learning that cause sensation
relationship
and about how it's tied to biological
cognitive mechanisms like experience
dependent plasticity
and then they tie that to several
specific mechanisms of cognitive
updating like the millisecond time scale
the minutes to hours time scale
and then the months to years and then
when we think about that forest that's
where we think about the
intergenerational selective extended
niche
anything else you'd add on this one
this is kind of the in between we're
going to get to the other side here
shortly when we go
further in the slides but
if you if you started thinking that if
if it was a simple matter of inverting
from walking on feet to walking on hands
this is kind of the in between between
okay so
to me it makes perfect sense it's
unsurprising that my skin is on the
outside and everything else is sort of
the bones and the and the organs and all
the blood is on the inside but to the
environment
they it has an inside and an outside as
well
and what is my outside could necessarily
be
the environments inside and this is kind
of transitioning us to that idea of yes
it would be surprising if everything
that's now currently inside of me was on
the outside
but stop looking at it as inversion in
that
sort of
centric or cellular way think of it now
in terms of the bigger picture
and that's where this i think this slide
starts transitioning us to that other
other perspective
awesome
okay continuing on
in section two
to figure one
all right
why don't you give a first pass
description on what you see in the
figure or what you think is important
about dean
well i'm going to read first before i
sort of throw my own comment in actions
are selected they bring about expected
outcomes while being geared toward
minimizing expected surprise or
uncertainty about the future
that's if you've been reading enough
stuff in active inference that you've
read that a few times
hence
inactive inference motor and autonomic
functions autonomic
work hand in hand
with a perceptual inference to resolve
uncertainty through the active sampling
of salient uncertainty reducing
sensations back to the feeling piece
while allowing for preferred
unsurprising outcomes free energy is
minimized with respect to counter
factual outcomes
and we've spoken a few times what what
is a counterfactual
in this context
but now it's very clear that the
counterfactual is embedded in a context
it doesn't just free float there are
times when it is supposed to now
extend into something or is already
embedded within something
by taking the expectation of free energy
under future outcomes given the action
being evaluated now
both daniel's copying my copy of the
paper didn't do a good job of
reproducing the purple and the greenness
of this
this world these two worlds and there's
a there's actually a third world going
to be introduced as well but
in order to be able to get to the idea
of extending
the first thing that they want to do is
kind of create this
idea of surprise minimization within a
tighter loop there's going to be a
concentric loop that they're going to
introduce around this
shortly
and that's what the all this is is is
just basically setting up i think for
the next figure but what do you think
daniel
yes just a few pieces to highlight and
then just describing it um this is a key
piece of active inference that there's a
relative comparison of expected futures
not just in the abstract
but always conditioned upon policy
affordances
and that helps us
determine whether to trim tab or steer
the ship to the left or to the right
because that's our affordances with our
hand on the rudder okay now if you're
modeling the hand on the rudder and a
hand on the gas and break that's another
control situation that you might be in
but there is no such thing as like the
neutral non-policy grounded trajectory
of the boat or
one could do that but it would actually
not be actionable it wouldn't be action
oriented because there would be like
some maximum likelihood boat trajectory
implicitly based upon non-action of the
captain
and it's like okay but i know that we're
gonna crash if we don't do anything
a biological organism is actually always
engaged in that action selection
and so this is both something that's
biologically grounding to always
condition upon policy affordances but
also is computationally simplifying
because we could have uncertainty about
both sides of the teammates but we still
need to act what do you think about that
before we continue well i think that's
that's fantastic because i think the
struggle that people have
in writing papers
is the fact that they're saying they're
talking right now because you have to
talk about the psychological niches how
do you keep in mind the functional
niches they've said you have to do that
but it's hard to do that when your focus
is on the cycle but but so how do you
keep
that other thing running in parallel the
functional niche while you're supposedly
giving your attentional
energies over to psychological niches
but you got to do it so how do you train
for that
that's what that's a fantastic thing
about this paper and what you just
kind of
explained again about active inference
it's a minimum of two if you lose one
you the whole thing falls apart
let's um
run around the rosie as it were
[Laughter]
so here even though the paper was quite
literally beyond skulls we're gonna have
a brain for the internal states
and so just looking at these four pieces
you could also kind of think about a
markov blanket in the middle but it's
not emphasized in this picture
what you see even without knowing what
the variables are is that these two on
the bottom right the internal states and
the action selection have this arg min
so those are as per this discussion
it means that it's an optimization
problem
so these two there's this active an act
of
optimization and selection and choice
here's the external states which it's a
stochastic differential equation so it's
doing some dynamics that's a function of
well omega noise term but also a
function of the current external states
as well as the actions
so if external states weren't influenced
in some way by action it would be for
naught
here's the sense states they're a
function of external states and noise
so you don't get to directly in the
instant of perception select sense
states
however
actions like
isocating ocular motor choices
can be selected
that result in changed sensory output
you can walk to a different part of the
room where you get a different
sensation of temperature
but
without um special appeals one can't
just
change their sensory inputs and so this
is like framing here's the
particular entity the blankets and the
internal states as partitioned off from
the external states
and even within the entity
we see that it's not enough just to talk
about the set of undirected nodes that
makes the internal and the external
states conditionally independent from
each other the mark called blanket this
is where we kind of get towards the
first and blanket where we're thinking
about incoming sensory dependencies
and treating those as perception
and then there's this free energy
function
that is doing perception as divergence
minimization
without the ability to directly control
those sensations
we also have action
as minimizing a divergence and
minimizing a bound on surprisal but this
is also framed as an optimization
that we actually get to choose based
upon our affordances and so this one is
kind of like you're selecting the
sensory
perceptive interpretive lens that is
minimizing something
it's minimizing surprisal and then in a
different way choosing from the action
selection
affordances there's also a minimization
of surprisal through action and so these
two are like choice driven optimization
like and then there also is this
optimization happening with perception
but it's like slightly different
can i just add something to that weekend
in all of these live streams
to go again and again back to the active
piece and the inference piece or the
action piece and the perception piece
but what i really liked about this
figure was if you actually again do a
little
little shift in terms of what you want
to pay attention to
back to the way
uploading or way up finding or whatever
right
you could say the bound
as minimized or you could say the bound
as
optimized and i think that's really
critical as well we can we can put all
of our attention on the perception in
the action or we could look at the bound
and what are the two meanings of
binding
and i get again if we're going to look
at this imaginally
what is the hudson river telling us
today
because that's that's now the bound as
optimized
doesn't necessarily have to have a plane
land on it
and the bound has minimized and i'll let
you use your imagination of what that
means
in that context right but again
there's multiple ways that this can be
parsed arbitrarily what we tend to focus
on is the action and the inference but
we could also look at so
how does this
how does this bound behave do we just
assume it's it's stationary it's static
it doesn't change
or
is it malleable
as well
i guess it just depends on what you want
to pay attention to right so again if we
it's this is going to lead to the next
figure which i really love
yes we'll get to figure two in a second
yep
um
they continue in section two one
discussing the
cognitive niche and this
there's a lot to say people could you
know pause the video and read these
quotations or they could read the paper
um
what would be the one or few things that
you would highlight from this and then
i'll give a thought
um
well i took i took from the paper the
the thing on the right bottom which in
red which i really like we do not claim
that the formal symmetry between brain
and niche
dynamics entails the symmetry and
construal
fantastic i'll let people they don't
know what construal is they can look
that up
rather we employ the notion of symmetry
epistemically as a modeling analog
to make sense of niche dynamics as
learning dynamics under active inference
they're just reassuring us that this is
through active inference
okay
the notion of symmetry is merely an
assumption
i think that that's
and if you read the paper
and you read that statement you'll go
okay they're not they're not overfitting
anything here
which i love
because it would be real easy to just go
completely off and start thinking
we've solved every riddle
they haven't done that they've done a
brilliant job of just sort of keeping it
in its lane
awesome so
to pick up on one of their quotes
uh they write the environment is the
generative process
that is modeled by the generative model
forest
generative model wayfinding hiking team
entailed by the phenotype
in virtue of the mathematical symmetry
imposed by a markov blanket that
separates or makes conditionally
independent the internal and external
states it's like hey whose side are you
on internal
is
external they're just
two sides
the environment can also be construed as
a generative model of its denizens
who now become the processes generating
outcomes for the environment so in
figure one
we had this sort of like argument on the
internal states but then it's a
different qualitative structure for
those generative processes
um so this might be appropriate for a
world where there's some active entity
that's doing strategy and cognition
and the rest of the world is like chains
of dominoes like there are
exogenous dynamics that could happen
without the cognitive entity pushing
them
but it's a mere active inference entity
in a sense
this formalism also could extend to
other cases but this is just sort of at
a first pass
and where we're headed and where we're
going to go in figure two in the next
slide is this symmetry as an assumption
and saying well actually let's put rich
dynamics on both sides of the blanket
let's allow this thinking where um one
active state of this entity is the sense
state of the other entity and vice versa
so
that means that niche construction is a
form of environmental learning
about the organisms hosted by the
environment so it's like the field
that's getting the pleasure path burnt
into it by footsteps it's actually in a
sense
learning where people like to walk
that's it's parameter updating
and then there's one case where
that pleasure path is just like the
stacks of dominoes and so it's like yes
it's parameter updating but it's kind of
like
low-key not learning
versus what if that pleasure path was
more and more agentic
more and more cognitive
then there's teaching going both
directions yeah and um
then we see a few examples like
um the the the two guys on this stream
you know here's the one that you put so
it's the person in nature and they're in
their vr viewing nature
that's like sort of this one which is
viewing viewing like that's the strange
loop part right and
the other thing too is if there was some
way that you could have put little vrs
on every one of those ants that would
have been kind of fascinating as well
because it and again it goes back to
when we when we look at slices in time
we can nest
and we're looking at a nest of ants but
is that the same thing
so
again it's it comes back to okay so i'm
just gonna say this at this point we'll
probably i'll probably have a ton of
bricks fall down on me but
you can look at things as as opposite
sides of the same coin or you can look
at twins
in both cases your the question is is
one better than the other or is it our
our ability to see both
that is the thing that matters
here's the um
twist with the ant picture
you'll notice that this ant has yellow
paints yellow paint on all three of its
body parts and this one has blue paint
and so it turns out that an experimenter
had previously collected these ants and
then
chilled them on ice and then while they
were stopped painted them carefully and
then reintroduced them to their colony
several hours later i did this in
arizona
so
now these painted ants and their
behavior they're like tracers in this
collective behavioral system
and so who's learning and who's teaching
from who
who's
training who there's cognitive entities
in a shared niche on both sides of the
markov blanket or whatever kind of
blanket however you draw it and so what
does it look like to start to embrace
this richness on both sides of the
cognitive partition
yeah let's see what that looks like in
figure two
okay so on the right side
um we have ye old figure one
way back when back when the environment
was simple weren't those the days
and
the figure has been updated in a few
different ways which i'll describe but
first what what did you see in figure 2
or what would you highlight here
okay well i'm gonna i'm gonna beat the
drum about
joint
self
evidencing so
i think we i think
it's easy enough to find out what
self-evidencing is
but joint outsell self-evidencing
is a whole different aunt or cat or
whatever
and so
when we introduce
the
niche construction optimizes the bound
on surprise now now the boundary
has a different look
what
why is that different than the first two
where is the where is the joint like
literally the joint
in this relationship because
relationship is fluid
how do we how do we secure exactly where
the joint is or is it
something that's more in the realm of
the twist you know back in the key words
we've got that image of the sort of the
morpheus strip
is that what's actually going on here as
opposed to sort of the more traditional
definition of what a joint is
awesome joint it's funny it means both
separate carve nature at the joints and
all that the joint between the two
pieces of plywood and it literally means
together they are joint it's like the
past tense of to join
it's a joint in the tensegrity sculpture
so that's a very interesting and what is
the difference between figure one and
figure two so the um triangle and the
star
so the idea of perception optimizing
surprisal we don't get to directly
control sensory states but we can
control our cognitive modeling of
sensory states
is bound on survival a surprisal
and a bound on survival in the
evolutionary sense and then action is
also this um argument like process of
choosing actions so that was in figure
one
now
rather than this external state just
being like a function of
external states and action states in a
noise term
now there's actually
this argument happening now it's an
argument on those same two arguments
it's still being influenced by the
current state of the external um states
and the actions
but now
the other side of the cognitive
partitioning is also doing
action selection
and so then they write
this effectively closes a circle of
causality in which the niche and
phenotypes i mean it's really just two
different phenotypes the niche and the
entity
are trying to learn about each other to
minimize their joint free energy or
surprise an inevitable consequence of
this is that the niche and its
incumbents
become mutually predictable
in both directions of fit
paging the principle of unitarity and
the quantum and the entanglement from 41
from 40.
so that the joint niche phenotype system
can be regarded as jointly
self-evidencing which probably also has
a few different ways to read it but we
had the star in the triangle
as perception and action as in the
common game of minimizing surprise for
the entity and now we have square
which is niche construction optimizing
the bound on surprise
of the niche
of the organism's actions which are
sense
from the perspective of the niche
like what if instead of
us trying to minimize our surprise about
co2 readings in the atmosphere
the other side of that coin is
the environment minimizing its surprise
about the co2 that's actually put in
and that's what about
yeah
what about the siamese twin example like
is that two sides of the same coin
right so again
this is the twist aspect of it this is
we're looking at the bound
as as opposed to
what's what's on the either on either
side of that again we have this ability
to see both it's a question of whether
we choose to
that's what's really that's what's
really great about this paper actually
because it's actually looking at
extending a mind but in order to be able
to do that it's asking you to can you
delimit
from what you're paying attention to
let's unpack the equations with one more
level so yep here we are in equation
four so
on the top left
we're going from figure one to figure
two
but with equation two to equation four
so
figure one
was here and then we introduced the
activity of the niche
equation
three
was the optimization of internal states
to infer causes
between this
and now
the niche is also going to be doing
something similar so equation four has
the same form as equation two
but with internal sensory and external
active states switch around
which is like
i switched um
um which
signpost was pointing to each side of
the maze and i switched where the food
locations were so it's still like the
sign is still correct but it's all
different now
this means that the variational density
is taken under the external
states not the internal states
and surprisal is relative to organisms
actions so from the organism's point of
view the variational density is over
internal states minimizing surprisal
about the environment
from the environment's point of view the
variational distribution is over
external states
and it is over
it is oriented towards reducing
surprisal relative to the organism's
actions but again environment and
organism it could just be thought of as
like side a and side b like whichever
side you're on there's going to be this
symmetry
in the forming
and
so that's what equation four does is it
pretty much just replicates equation two
but instead of um
it being about the organism
doing free energy minimization on
sensations and
internal states
it's literally the other two pieces
of the quadrivium of the fourfold
distinction which is like it's a free
energy minimization of the environments
on the actions of the organism and the
current state of the environment
and then there's analogous flippings of
all the other pieces
so
that's basically taking this symmetry
seriously
and it shows that this free energy
functional
structure
it is like it's enough to hold the yes
and the no or to hold both sides
together
it's not a jedi mind trick to say that
my outsides
can be inside
the insides of something else like that
that's
that that is literally not hard to do
but that's not necessarily how i don't
walk around every day identifying myself
as the insides of something
larger
right but that's a fact
so
yeah and it's almost like the um inside
out view on strategy
it ends up through thinking through
other minds being like an outside in
strategy
other strategic entities the other chess
player
how will they
think about my actions
and so it's like stepping outside of the
entity
considering how other minds
will see the entity's actions as sense
states
yeah
perfect all right great
2.2
the psychological niche so this is where
they're going to be unpacking the
cognitive niche concept again in terms
of like the functional and the
psychological components
and um
any things here before all just note
whatever i see yeah and then the thing
you've just highlighted the
psychological niche can thus be viewed
as a state space of invitations to act
that's that's the attractor state thing
i think i don't want to overstep but i
think that's what it's sort of pointing
to
uh with peaks and valleys that
correspond to the most and least
probable and thereby adaptive actions
given the priors and phenotypic
preferences of organisms like me
having constructed the niche in the
first place and i brought those three
images in
as examples of why free energy minimize
drive niche construction in states they
share with these
psychological attractors like why does
somebody want to paraglide
outside of the launch in switzerland or
do the ferrata
on mount norquay and banff or
i'm not sure where that where the
amusement park is in the states but i
mean again why are these
why are these could be these
not just functional places but
psychological
niches right as an extension of the mind
that's essentially what this is
is is pointing at do we necessarily see
the walking along that ferrata as an
extension of the mind well
people that are probably enjoying it do
and people that are wetting themselves
probably don't
[Laughter]
and all of these cases
involve
the cognitive niche broadly as having
like a functional underlying physical
embodied substrate like there is a
roller coaster here there is a
bridge of some kind there is the
apparatus of the paragliding machinery
and it's both functional and it's
cognitive it's an invitation
for an experience and an invitation for
being in a certain scenario
so that's very rich and i hope we can
explore that a little more
in the
one too
and it's also it's also yeah it's also
dense and it's also up and down
which in the previous slide we saw the
i'm sorry i think it's the previous
slide where we saw the the waves
example
one one of the i'm not sure if it's
slide 23 or 24
but anyway that's the other part of this
the psychological piece it's it's not
necessarily stable
you don't know who's going to walk into
these kind of
uh niche constructions and remain stable
and who's going to be completely
destabilized by what they find
themselves and that surprisal piece
causes all kinds of feelings right so
yeah it's
again fantastic paper
great
we come now to section two three the
functional niche so previously we were
discussing that psychological niche
facet of the cognitive niche and then
this is going to the functional niche
what does dancing with the stars have to
do with it or what would you add here
well
do we gear learning towards belonging to
or working with or both
because i think in in in different
situations that we find ourselves
sometimes we're
partnered with somebody who has prior
experience sometimes we're stepping on
one another's toes
and either one of those kind of
situations
can bring us minimize our free energy
right and optimize
i step on you step on my toes enough
times i'll probably communicate to you
that we need to maybe change the pattern
of your foot movement
right one isn't one isn't always done at
the exclusion of the other in terms of
getting to the place we want to be
sooner there's also the part where
dancing and and actual
galactic
scales just fascinates me
[Laughter]
um i'm going to start with a quote in
the paper but it will end in a joke um
they give this example of the wax
feeling and extendative cognitive
apparatus of like the whole postal
chain the supply chain logistics of the
mailing
yeah and
they basically say the point here is
neither
uh is that neither of the internal or
external
subcomponents of the brainwax system
exists in isolation so it's like the
fully distributed term so what does it
look like when instead of just thinking
like well
cognition is about what's happening in
the brain happening in the skull
and then there's all these extensions of
cognition like that get um facilitating
what happens in the brain is now going
to be done through these extended
apparatuses and this is kind of like
even going further which is like yeah
it's a little odd to depict the wax as
doing active modeling of the punch
but
actually from the markov partitioning
perspective all these different sub
components of the cognitive
constellation federation
are all
sense and acting each other they're all
doing active on each other
back to figure two
look at the brain
see how it has a star here perception
optimizing the balance of
so how do we dance with the stars
how do we do group dancing with the
stars
how do the brains dance together
that's not the same thing as one active
brain one star
in an extended dead universe
dancing with the stars is when
cognitive entities
are on the other side of the phone
and so it's a very apt
meme that you added here
there's another interesting part to this
too and that is the stage tends to be
set up so that the cameras can catch all
of the
the choreography what happens when the
participants
impose on the cameras right like when
did they extend the stage out into the
audience like that that hasn't happened
yet but what would that mean then for
the property that we know had
conventionally have known as dancing
with the stars
now the camera has to move
to that
active inference
that that's imposing and it's kind of
really fascinating again
do you do you construct it and contain
it
or
what what what elements of this are
actually
free and independent
that makes me think about um
[Music]
here's figure one science communication
scientists are
stars and they're great
figure two science communication
now we're dancing with the stars because
the fourth wall has been broken
and there's
rich cognitive activity
not just happening on both sides of the
communication partition but actually in
a way where it's irreducible and it's a
value add from both sides that's when
we'll be doing science communication
with the stars
okay yep
two four um we won't go into it that
much but feel free to make any um
comment that you like they give a case
study
of the common earthworm
lumber chris
terrestris so here's that wormy guy
and they talk about some of the ideas
that were brought up in the previous
sections like
counterfactuals in the niche and
inferential efficiency and
uh uploading of cognitive functions
in the context of the worm anything
you'd add about this or we can continue
on
just real quickly i mean i'm glad that
they're introducing the second not just
offloading but uploading but again i'm
always sort of i always get a little
sensitive around the idea that
expediting
is not expedition and and we we are sort
of built to do both
so optimization can sometimes just
take take a longer path
and so i'm again i'm not i'm not
critiquing what they're saying here i
understand what in the context of
earthworms i don't know if there's a
a magellan earthworm and or if one has
been discovered yet
so i i don't want to sort of drag this
off into the into the wilderness but i
do know that for us
there is
that aspect of our curiosity which we
want to make sure that we don't toss
away in terms of
bringing
the example of the case study for
cool
just one note here um
over multiple generations
so that's both ecological in terms of
the stigmatic niche construction of
building the tunnel apparatus and it's
evolutionary because there's a selective
niche now inside of the ecological niche
that selects for earthworms that are
better at for example using tunnels and
buildings sometimes rather than being
the builder earthworm
this comes at the cost of being
evolutionarily glued to those cognitive
extensions put bluntly
cognitive niche construction smartens
the world of the earthworm so that its
physiology can remain dumb yet optimal
in peace
so from 24 years ago clark
and so that's interesting to think about
and it actually relates to a question
that um joseph clarke asked in the chat
um they wrote if we can model the
environment as a sum of its states and
the state's
environment
what does this stay about what does this
say about our capacity to create a super
intelligence
perhaps in an adapted structure to
the deep generative model of mental
action with the super intelligence
acting as a tension over its states like
people and frogs
so this is kind of like saying
okay um
well just one thought it's not exactly
what is being said is all right so we've
talked about how there's this like
extended active inference that's
happening
richly in a distributed way across
multiple stars we're doing active with
the stars
but is that whole system
one
non-extended super intelligence
or what is that
extended system and what does that say
about our ability to actually construct
and work with different intelligences
than human
cool
um three
extended active inference so here's
where we get to the eai parts
what would you say about this
well um
i have a lot to say but honestly i think
i want to keep it to the point one on
the point too because they're they're
i'm not
by nature the kind of person who wants
to critique and i'm not critiquing this
but i can think of lots and lots of
examples in my
my personal professional
uh history where
if you don't appreciate put bluntly
cognitive niche construction smartens
the world of the earthworm so that its
physiology can remain dumb yet optimal
in peace that's been ignored in a lot of
formal education settings so if we get
there we'll talk about it and if we
don't
no problem
great they do connect to
um at least two minimum of two of course
and these are like extended in space and
extended in time through time diacronic
as opposed to sin chronic and so without
um
going too
much into the quantum
wormhole rabbit hole with space and time
being constructs hashtag livestream4d
those are at least just two ways we can
think about extended cognition
okay
here's the sections that are in three
and it'll be great to talk more about
this in
one and two
in these sections they introduce
three functions or aspects of the
extended mind
so
the first of these
features as they call them is a parity
principle
the parity principle states that
if a part of the world functions as a
process which
weren't done in the head we would have
no hesitation in recognizing it as part
of the cognitive process then that part
of the world is
part of the cognitive process so if you
can add two plus two in your head be
right or wrong or whatever
then it shouldn't be um qualitatively
different
to think about two plus two on the
calculator it's all part of this
extended cognitive so parity just means
like um
if it's been rendered under caesar then
it's equal
the parity principle yeah
okay no no that's that's right yeah the
parity principle entails the second
feature of the theory of extended mind
which is the notion of a potential
functional isomorphism between some
internal and external states
we discuss this a lot in the
representations paper and what does
active inference tell us about our
representations of ourself and all of
that so
there's
a lot
packed into this notion of functional
isomorphism what kind of functional
isomorphism does the cognitive model
have the same structure as the
generative process or can it be just
action oriented and of a totally
different kind
but
suffice to say there has to be some
functional connection
and then the third piece that they
introduce is this epistemic action
these are actions that ease or optimize
cognitive tasks by reducing the memory
load
required to perform a task so that's
like space complexity
by simplifying the computational
processing procedure
time complexity
and by minimizing the probability of
error outcomes success probabilities
so it's kind of like space time and then
surprise
and that's the cognitive dimension like
we always hear about what would it be
like when you're on the light beam and
when you're on the spaceship and when
you're going into the black hole
in this objectivist frame
as if the dimensions that mattered were
like the objective space and time but
once we swallow that cognitive pill or
decide to let it course through us in
our action
all of a sudden there's the surprise
dimension
the element of surprise
and that's where some of these
psychological aspects of the cognitive
niche come into play
and some of these citations are pretty
interesting so as always like reading
citations is awesome
um
so
referring to the first of those features
that they talk about with the parity
principle
it's been suggested that external
resources should meet the requirements
of glue and trust
so it's not just for first graders
anymore glue and trust
so that the resource is available when
needed like biomemory and not subject to
constant agentive scrutiny
to ensure it is working as it should
again like biomimicry biomembrane sorry
in the point of view of extended active
inference the trust condition is
guaranteed by the uploading process
whereby the agent learns to engage
epistemic cues of the generative process
this entails trading off
onboard neurocognitive functions
for
on-board environmental ones i wasn't
actually sure if this was meant to be
off-boarded
environmental ones or if on-board here
is still referring to our ship it's
still on board our ship but
now the function is also distributed
environmentally
yeah
but i i i kind of focused on the
trade-off
so
it's it's
you you you made a choice
now was it the was it the proper one you
won't you you hope that the stability of
the thing that you
that you've passed along to
remains robust and
and constant
so that's why it's a trade-off there's
an assumption built in i think that's
how i read it
and they also write like for instance
the earthworm is glued to its
inheritance of burrows and moist soil
because the constraints of burrows soils
etc have played on the earthworms
evolution
and then um we can imagine how an
individual would become glued to their
environment in a similar fashion over
developmental and also evolutionary time
skills like if we
don't have fossil fuels tomorrow it's
going to be tough but there would have
been a time previously in history before
we were glued to them like we are now
and so it's like glue and trust and
what does that enable what does it
constrain and how does that relate to
this course graining and the parity
principle
okay epistemic actions so they write uh
a notebook for instance can be viewed as
supporting and easing the task of making
it to your multiple appointments
throughout the week because it can
encode relevant information
it can provide structures like a
schedule and it can increase your
chances of making it to those
appointments on time so it's the same
three
areas that we discussed earlier like
space time and
surprise
about success
these intuitions are formalized by the
process of uploading from the point of
view of extended active inference but in
addition by accounting for the relation
between all these advantages
also between slash among between is for
two things and among us for more than
two things
um and then here's a bunch of different
kinds of notebooks and then here's the
computational one
anything to add on this
well traditionally i mean from a from a
learning standpoint that the
the epistemic actions tend to be placed
into a planning paradigm whereas i see
this more as the provisioning
this is part of
my kit
so i kind of tend to step back and say
um
a journal
a journal by itself or an assumption
that journaling writing my ideas out in
the traditional sense
um
isn't the same as i'm going to bring a
journal along in case
and then the encase being the counter
factual right
so again i'm in agreement with them but
i don't necessarily i know that
that
convention follows that you take one of
these things along because you're
planning
and i'm not discounting planning i'm
just saying when it turns into a plan as
opposed to it's one more
source of uh or one more example of a
provisioning exercise
yes um one thought on that would be like
the difference between
um true step-by-step long-term planning
planning as inference
and
a sort of nested planning approach where
it's like today i'm just gonna plan to
make time to pack my backpack
and then
i'll have a plan in the moment when i'm
there with my backpack like i want to
have the best possible plan but we're
like layers of uncertainty away from
what actually might be that situation or
the specifics
but i want to have the right affordances
then
and so what are the plans that can be
taken right now
so that we can
plan to plan
instead of just treating planning as
like being like before action and being
like we're just going to be in the
headquarters and we're going to plan out
all the alternatives
it's like how are we going to plan to
plan and then once you go into the
nested planning well then how are we
going to plan to plan to plan and what
should we be doing in the headquarters
maybe we should be
on the road by now
yeah
well it's just it's different versions
and i think and as long as you can see
them as being different
you're probably ahead of the person who
automatically
jumps to one conclusion of what this
means so that's all
great and then one other term um that
they
talked about is on diachronic cognition
so they wrote the standard example used
to explain diachronic cognition is that
of elizabethan theater companies
uh in the work of triple 2005 evelyn
triple distributing cognition in the
globe
theater
and this paper is about how members of
theater companies during the 16th
century ad would manage to perform
multiple plays per week without being
able to rehearse due to time limitations
so
too real too real
and the ability of the actors to
memorize how to perform those plays
depended on
all kinds of embodied enacted and
cultured et cetera et cetera et cetera
like all the richness
was there and is there
and um then like this is just one quote
from tribble's paper and then love to
hear what you think about it
so here's from king lear which is a
shakespeare play that i love
um
[Music]
and
it's just interesting
in this extended cognitive discussion
to see the artifact of the text
the written part that's like the trace
that we see and that's um when when
fristen speaks of singing from the same
hymn sheet this is kind of like this is
the script i mean isn't the script like
the dna isn't it the blueprint
and then this actually reminds us that
no there's actually hundreds of years of
discourse and discussion
around the enactments and what the trace
means
and so like
meager argues what has eluded
generations of editors
is not likely to have been instantly
grasped by the company originally
mobilizing the play
meager argues that shakespeare was
expected
probably and preferred to be available
plan to plan to speak to will
get in the boat
able to explain and install such designs
as this yeah
captain shakespeare was expected to be
there and so that's why the trace isn't
instructions
it's kind of interesting too if you
think about this because what does this
say about a lot of stuff that goes on at
the post-secondary level now which
you
put a loop on it or put a bow on it when
you when you
have a conversation with somebody about
your poster or your trifold
what is what has that got to do with a a
a diachronic cognition
um
interesting right because
it's not the same thing what they're
what they're essentially saying here is
there's
there's the context of how you would
present a poster
but then there's this
which is appears
i guess to the to the to the current
viewer not the one 500 years ago as
being this this thing being taking up a
lot more time
but back then
that was the default
for those people who are time
constrained
so
again do we have it we have have we have
we come up with a way of being able to
demonstrate
cognition today
that
um
enables
this
view
i don't know i'm not i'm not again i'm
not criticizing i'm just saying what if
counterfactually
this were the way that we were able to
now give people an opportunity to say
this was my niche construction as
opposed to i got x number
of answers correct on this form of
filter
yeah when you when
um
this paper
talks about pattern sociocultural
practices mediated by material artifacts
populating the stage and across
generational apprenticeship system and
what you just said about
education this makes me think about the
phd
system
and the idea that it could happen
without the materiality
or the intergenerational mentorship and
apprenticeship systems
um
it just wouldn't be the same cognitive
system and i really liked what you said
there like the brain
based
instructionist paradigm it it wants to
put the student in the cubicle
into a different niche a different
learning environment and then test them
on the recall on the ability to like be
that api on the other side of the
question response hotline
and what else does it look like when we
invite
each student to create a cognitive niche
which as we're discussing here is
psychological
and it's offloaded it's uploaded into
the environment which could be digital
and then it's like i want to know that
you spent the time and attention
i want to see your coda page with the
questions that you wrote and i want to
see some components of your cognitive
niche
and see where you're developing it and
how you're developing it and
public goods like parks there's people
who prune the roses and there's people
who mow the grass there's people who
make sure the trees are all good to go
and those are all different kinds of
niche maintenance practices
and so in our
broader
cognitive niche
how do we
navigate
man
here's their whole concluding stage
right
yeah
here's their whole concluding remark
um the model of cognitive niche
construction proposed in this paper
offers a formal apparatus for the study
of non-brace non-brain based factors in
cognition
so
extended cognition as a starting point
for modeling
not as a conclusion not like well
there's all these things in the niche
and there's the apprenticeship and then
there's the ambiguity and so the
conclusion of my paper is
it's extended
invert
that
so that it's right
starting with the notion of this
extended distributed cognitive process
and then apply the sense making
to the modeling process in this holistic
way
the point stressed in the paper
was that cognitive niche construction
can be studied as a shared cognitive
functioning
enabling organisms to track
fractal
often implicitly and at low cost
and fractal
cause effect relationships
otherwise difficult if not impossible to
track
semicolon
notably relationships where the causal
structure is volatile
or too complex to be learned
by a single entity by a single nest mate
and so as they close from the point of
view of extended active inference eai
all cognitive functions are in the game
of tracking causal regularities and
there's no principled reason to restrict
this process to the boundaries of skin
skull
or even individual agents
so then how do we put it all into
practice
what does applied extended active
inference looks like
um yes
the four e a cognitive extended embedded
and cultured inactive applied cognition
and so definitely when we're in 41.1
we can talk about
applied slash applying
i'm taking initiative
that's a really critical thing like it's
hard to do
you always hear people in in
post-secondary education say well it's
what you do with it it's right like
there's a bit of a hand wiping aspect
what's what you do with it
but what this is saying is
i think it's a little bit more than
what i do with it so how do we set that
stage
so that it's not quite
so daunting to take the initiative
the the what you do with it is the
hands-on that's you're the active person
it's what you make of it it's the energy
you put in you're going to get back what
you put into your phd
that's
you're the star of the show you're the
main and only character in this dead
extended cognitive worlds
right but what about when we're dancing
with the phds and non-phds
and we're actually applying together in
a shared cognitive niche
and that cognitive niche includes other
stars who are also like sensing and
acting and cognizing about us so applied
thinking through other minds and ways of
knowing
and then
another question that we'll discuss in
dot one
dave
was that there's often a point in these
active papers
about
the um different kinds of partitioning
and blankets there's anatomical
mechanical there's functional
psychological but there's a lot of
different partitionings and different
kinds of things come into play so what
is the relation
between the anatomical mechanical
blankets
so the skin and skull
yep and the functional psychological
blankets this is kind of like brain and
mind
so how is that distinction related to
nesting
of similar or different kinds of
blankets
and then
oh yeah where does the niche
and the niches and the niches of each
other and the laterally interacting and
the nested niches
how does that all come together
so yeah
what are your penultimate thoughts dean
well first of all i really appreciate
the paper i think it's a fantastic paper
it's it's it i love inverting because i
think we're capable of doing that to
dave's point um i think we have this
ability to see the difference between
process and product or
up and down or whatever dynamic and
stable
and arbitrariness
seems to
bother the people who want things to be
stable and stability seems to bother
those people that want things to be
creative and i think that's a perfect
world
and so
every time i read one of these papers by
axel and the other authors but
in particular the two papers recently
that we've now given a treatment to that
i think axel was the primary author
first author
only author on 34 yes yeah i mean he he
he brings things that
at first
our
might seem counterintuitive compared to
the way things traditionally have been
viewed
and he makes a very compelling case for
why we might want to open a second eye
to this he doesn't throw out
the first thing he says maybe there's a
new entailment that we might want to
consider in this partitioning exercise
we all
seem to participate in just
different levels of degrees of
sophistication so
again i don't i'm not a i'm not a fanboy
or uh you know putting people up on
pedestals but i certainly respect
uh
the way that he's able to share this
information and make it more accessible
i think we can make it even more
accessible if we can find real life on
the ground examples and i think that's
what we'll try to do in the forty one
one and two
awesome agreed um
axel gets those cogs spinning so as
always axel thanks for the collaboration
directly and indirectly and yeah this
should be a great
set of discussions in the dot one and
dot two so
dean thanks a ton for all the assistance
uh before during and after here
and uh
to anyone else who's listening now or in
the future or whenever just
come
get involved and enact
with us all the world's a stage
everyone's a critic we're all stars here
etc
thanks daniel really appreciate it bye
you